Edward Corsi Papers
Edward Corsi Papers
1918-1968
Corsi, Edward, 1896-1965
30 linear ft.
Papers of the author and government official, active in the areas of immigration, labor relations, and social welfare. Correspondence (1922-1965); writings (1922-1956); organizational activities files (1918-1965); and published material (1931-1966). Notable correspondents include the America-Italy Society, Inc., American Council for Nationalities Service, American Federation of International Institutes, American Museum of Immigration, Anthony Celebrezze, Common Council for American Unity, Allen W. Dulles, John Foster Dulles, W. Averell Harriman, Herbert Hoover, Italian Historical Society of America, Irving M. Ives, Jacob K. Javits, Fiorello H. La Guardia, La Guardia Memorial House, Inc., William Lescaze, National Committee on Immigration Policy, National Council on Naturalization and Citizenship, Order Sons of Italy in America, Frances Perkins, Republican Party, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Howard A. Smith, Ralph W. Sockman, United Neighborhood Houses of New York, Inc., U.S. Immigration and Naturalization Service, and others.
148905
Biographical History
[Photo at right: Edward Corsi]
Edward Corsi (1896-1965) was an Italian-American association executive and government official, particularly active in the areas of immigration, labor relations, and social welfare.
Born in Italy on December 29, 1896, the son of Philip Frederick and Julia (Pantano) Corsi, he entered America with his family in 1906. The Corsi family settled in New York City, and Edward attended Clason Point Military Academy and Saint Francis Xavier College. He became a naturalized citizen in 1921 and the following year received his LL.B. degree from Fordham University.
Before graduating from Fordham, Mr. Corsi had joined the staff of Haarlem House in East Harlem, which offered educational and recreational services for the local Italian-American community (it later became LaGuardia Memorial House). There he met Emma Gillies, a social worker, and they were married June 17, 1926. Their son, Philip Donald, was born in 1928.
During these years, Mr. Corsi became a well-known writer and speaker about the foreign-born. In 1923 he wrote several articles about Mexico for The Outlook and later a description of Mussolini's Italy for The World. He became the director of Haarlem House in 1926.
Mr. Corsi's government career began in 1930, when he was appointed supervisor of a census district in New York City. In 1931 Herbert Hoover appointed him Commissioner of Immigration at Ellis Island, where Mr. Corsi humanized the entry procedures, and in 1933 he was reappointed by President Roosevelt as Commissioner of Immigration and Naturalization. In 1934 Mayor Fiorello LaGuardia asked Mr. Corsi to serve as director of the Home Relief Fund for New York City. An appointment as Deputy Commissioner for the New York City Department of Public Welfare followed.
As a delegate-at-large to the New York State Constitutional Convention in 1938, Mr. Corsi was chairman of the Social Welfare Committee and a member of the Labor Committee; in these capacities he successfully sponsored the amendments providing for unemployment insurance, sickness and old-age benefits, the care of the needy and the promotion of public health. In 1938 he ran unsuccessfully as Republican candidate for the United States Senate.
During the early years of World War II, Mr. Corsi was appointed chairman of the Alien Enemy Hearing Board, Southern District of New York State. Governor Thomas E. Dewey appointed him chairman of the New York State Industrial Board in March of 1943, and in November of that year he was appointed Industrial Commissioner of the New York State Department of Labor, serving until 1955. In 1950 he was Republican candidate for mayor of New York City but was defeated by Vincent Impelliteri.
In December 1954, Mr. Corsi was requested to serve as Special Assistant to the Secretary of State for Refugee and Migration Problems. Following his resignation from the Washington post in April 1955, he returned to New York to resume his work at LaGuardia Memorial House.
Mr. Corsi continued to participate actively in the many organizations with which he was associated. Throughout his life he was a member and sponsor of groups connected with immigration and the problems of the foreign-born, the poor, Italian-Americans, and labor unions. He was a trustee of Cornell University, a Knight Commander of the Republic of Italy, and the author of In the Shadow Liberty (1935) and Pathways to the New World (1940). Mr. Corsi died on December 13, 1965, as the result of an automobile accident.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Edward Corsi Papers, although largely correspondence, also contain biographical data, financial records, writings, published material and papers representing each of his specific activities.
Biographical data, 1904-1968, contains biographical sketches written about Mr. Corsi during his lifetime. Other material includes awards, ephemera, obituaries and memorials which contain tributes to Mr. Corsi and plans for the Corsi Labor-Management Relations Institute of Pace College. Printed material representing social functions and conferences Mr. Corsi attended are included in memorabilia. Photographs of Mr. Corsi, annotated by his secretary, are chronologically arranged, as are newspaper clippings about Mr. Corsi's activities.
Correspondence, 1922-1965, is both incoming and outgoing and is primarily business correspondence, although some personal letters are included. The letters contain personal requests from business associates, inter-office memoranda, letters of recommendation, correspondence among New York State government agencies and private organizations, and general business correspondence. A group of lists (Box 27), chronologically arranged, contains names and addresses of correspondents compiled by Mr. Corsi's staff.
The collection includes correspondence with the following persons of interest, with inclusive dates of the letters:
America-Italy Society, Inc., 1951-1965
American Council for Nationalities Service, 1961-1965
Bixby, R. Burdell, 1948-1954
Boothe, Clare (Clare Boothe Luce), 1953
Boys' Towns of Italy, Inc., 1951-1965
Breitel, Charles D., 1943-1949
Burton, John Edward, 1943-1950
Celebrezze, Anthony, 1963-1965
Common Council for American Unity, 1943-1955
Corsi, Angelo, 1951-1964
Corsi, Edward, and Associates, Inc., 1941-1943
Costello, Frank J., 1948
Curran, Thomas J, 1947-1955
DeGasperi, Alcide, 1948
Dulles, Allen W., 1953-1954
Dulles, John Foster, 1949-1955
Eisenhower, Dwight D., 1955
Freedom House, 1951-1954
Hagerty, James C., 1953, 1955
Harriman, W. Averell, 1948, 1956
Hoover, Herbert, 1930-1955
Italian Historical Society of America, 1949-1960
Ives, Irving M., 1948-1955
Javits, Jacob K., 1951-1965
Johnson, Charles F., Jr., 1950
LaGuardia, Fiorello H., 1935-1947
Lescaze, William, 1963
Lindbergh, Charles A., 1930
Mitchell, James P., 1954
Nardi, Luigi, 1946-1949
New York State Department of Labor, 1943-1958
New York State Workmen's Compensation Board, 1942-1953
O'Brien, Lawrence F., 1965
Perkins, Frances, 1943-1949
Rabb, Maxwell M., 1954-1955
Rockefeller, Nelson A., 1961-1965
Skouras, Spyros P., 1941-1965
Smith, Howard A., 1950-1953
Sockman, Ralph W., 1949
Stephens, Thomas E., 1952-1953
Tarchiani, Alberto, 1945-1954
Thomas, Norman, 1962, 1964
Tolley, William P., 1952
United Neighborhood Houses of New York, Inc., 1952-1965
United States Department of Justice, Immigration and Naturalization Service, 1943-1955
Weeks, Sinclair, 1953
Willkie, Wendell L., 1940, 1943
Correspondence of others, 1931-1967, includes a few of Mrs. Corsi's letters and the many condolences she received after Mr. Corsi's death.
Financial records, 1940-1965, include some tax returns, a few bills paid, correspondence about financial matters, and health insurance papers.
Mr. Corsi's Writings from 1922-1956 represent his varied interests. Articles include his early material about Mexico and Italy published in Outlook. Other articles are "Salute to a Lady," several dealing with immigration, and a series on Yugoslavia. Books contains material relating to those written by Mr. Corsi; supporting material for In the Shadow of Liberty includes correspondence and book reviews while Pathways to a New World is represented by a paperback edition published in 1953 under the title Paths to a New World. Radio broadcasts in Italian, most of them typescripts, date from 1941 to 1947 A number of Mr. Corsi's speeches, 1938-1956, are included in the collection; their content illustrates Mr. Corsi's interests in immigration, the foreign-born, labor and employment and his state public administrative work in New York State. Some indication of the content of untitled speeches is supplied in the shelf list. Speeches preceded by an asterisk (*) in the shelf list were broadcast by radio. A small group of the writings of others includes an untitled book on crime-fighting by Michael Fiaschetti, an article by Louis Adamic, and an article on the sculptor, Massari.
Activities, 1918-1965, form a special section devoted to materials from various committees, campaigns, agencies and charities for which Mr. Corsi worked. Material filed with each activity group includes correspondence, agenda, minutes of meetings, reports, proposals, published material and legal cases. Of particular interest are the files on Thomas E. Dewey, immigration and naturalization, and LaGuardia Memorial House, Inc.
Published material, 1931-1966, includes the periodical La Settimana, "rivista italiana fondata da Edward Corsi," as well as material on the Executive Branch Liaison office under the Eisenhower administration, farming and gardening, foreign aid, the Frank Erickson gambling inquiry, Italy, labor and unemployment, and the Day Care Division of the New York Bureau of Child Welfare.
Arrangement of the Collection
Biographical material is arranged alphabetically by type; within that, photographs and newspaper clippings are further arranged chronologically. Correspondence (both Corsi's and that of others) is arranged chronologically. Financial records are arranged chronologically. Wrirings are arranged alphabetically by type; within that, they are arranged either alphabetically by title (articles, books) or chronologically (radio addresses, speeches). Activities material is arranged alphabetically by organization name. Published material is arranged alphabetically by title.
Subject and Genre Headings
New York State; Politics, government and public administration; Celebrezze, Anthony J. (Anthony Joseph), 1910-; Corsi, Edward, 1896-1965 -- Archives.; Dulles, Allen Welsh, 1893-1969.; Dulles, John Foster, 1888-1959.; Harriman, W. Averell (William Averell), 1891-1986.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; Italian Historical Society of America.; Ives, Irving McNeil, 1896-1962.; Javits, Jacob K. (Jacob Koppel), 1904-1986.; La Guardia, Fiorello H. (Fiorello Henry), 1882-1947.; LaGuardia Memorial House, Inc.; Lescaze, William, 1896-1969.; Perkins, Frances, 1880-1965.; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979.; Smith, H. Alexander (Howard Alexander), 1880-1966.; Sockman, Ralph W. (Ralph Washington), 1889-1970.; America-Italy Society, Inc.; American Council for Nationalities Service.; American Federation of International Institutes.; American Museum of Immigration.; Common Council for American Unity.; National Committee on Immigration Policy (U.S.); National Council on Naturalization and Citizenship (U.S.); Order Sons of Italy in America.; Republican Party (U.S.); United Neighborhood Houses of New York, Inc.; United States. -- Immigration and Naturalization Service.; Arbitration, Industrial.; Authors, American.; Political campaigns -- New York (State); Italian Americans.; United States -- Emigration and immigration.; United States -- Officials and employees.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Photographs.; Speeches (documents); Authors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
The interview with John Foster Dulles is restricted as follows: Princeton University Library supplied Syracuse University Library Manuscript Division a copy of the interview with Mrs. Corsi's knowledge and consent, and accepted the following restrictions on the use of the transcript: "That it may be read in the Princeton [Syracuse] University Library, quoted from, and cited only by serious research scholars accredited by Princeton [Syracuse] University. The Princeton [Syracuse] University Library is authorized to supply a single photocopy to any scholar thus accredited. This transcript may not be otherwise reproduced, either in whole or in part, by microphoto, typewriter, photostat, or any other device, except by the heirs, legal representatives, or assigns of Commissioner Edward Corsi."
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. Edward Corsi, 1966-1969.
Inventory
- Biographical data
  - Biographical sketches, correspondence, 1935; 1946-1947,; Jan 1952- Mar 1964,; undated; typescript and printed material (Box 1)
  - "Al merito della republica Italiana" award, June 2, 1955 (Oversize 1)
  - Awards, Apr 1939-Jan 1966 (Box 1)
  - Obituaries, Dec 1965-Jan 1966; printed material (Box 1)
  - Memorials, December 1965-November 1968; printed material (Box 1)
  - Memorabilia, October 1931-September 1949; May 1950-May 1965,; undated; printed material; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Ephemera, November 1931-May 1955; printed material (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - 1931-April 1947 (Box 2)
    - Luncheon for ambassadors of Italy, November 14 1946 (Oversize 1)
    - August 1948 (Box 2)
    - September 1948-January 1950 (Box 2)
    - Corsi testimonial dinner, May 24 1950 (Oversize 1)
    - September-December 1950 (Box 2)
    - 1951-1961 (Box 2)
    - September 1948-January 1950, September-December 1950, 1951-1961 (Box 2)
    - May 1962-May 1966 (Box 2)
    - Undated, 7 folders (Box 2)
    - Corsi Family, 1904; undated (Box 3)
    - Corsi and Eisenhower, Undated; 2 items (Oversize 1)
    - Unidentified oversize, Undated; 2 items (Oversize 1)
  - Newspaper clippings
    - June 19, 1928-October 29, 1933 (Box 3)
    - January 15, 1934-November 7, 1938 (Box 3)
    - August 29, 1940-December 14, 1945 (Box 3)
    - January 18, 1946-May 20, 1946 (Box 3)
    - June 10, 1946-October 23, 1946 (Box 3)
    - March 6, 1947-December 9, 1948 (Box 3)
    - January 10, 1949-April 20, 1949 (Box 4)
    - June 20, 1949-November 29, 1949 (Box 4)
    - March 3, 1950-June 13, 1951 (Box 4)
    - May 12, 1952-December 30, 1954 (Box 4)
    - January 5, 1955-April 8, 1955 (Box 4)
    - April, 1955, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - [April? 1955] re: Corsi-Dulles Dispute (Box 5)
    - May 1, 1955-May 1, 1966 (Box 5)
    - Undated (Box 5)
- Correspondence
  - 1922, August 25 (Box 5)
  - 1923, November 1 (Box 5)
  - 1931, June 29-1939, April 5 (Box 5)
  - 1940 (Box 5)
  - 1941, January-October, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - 1941, November-December (Box 6)
  - 1942, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - 1943, January-July, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - 1943, August-December, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - 1944, January-May (Box 7)
  - 1944, June-December, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - 1945 January-July, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - 1945 August-December, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - 1946 January-October, 4 folders (Box 9)
  - 1946 November-December (Box 10)
  - 1947 January-July, 6 folders (Box 10)
  - 1947 August-December, 5 folders (Box 11)
  - 1948 January-February, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - 1948 March-September, 7 folders (Box 12)
  - 1948 October-December, 4 folders (Box 13)
  - 1949 January-March, 3 folders (Box 13)
  - 1949 April-November, 7 folders (Box 14)
  - 1949 December (Box 15)
  - 1950 January-June, 6 folders (Box 15)
  - 1950 July-December, 5 folders (Box 16)
  - 1951 January-February, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - 1951 March-November, 7 folders (Box 17)
  - 1951 December (Box 18)
  - 1952 January-July, 5 folders (Box 18)
  - 1952 August-December, 5 folders (Box 19)
  - 1953 January-March, 3 folders (Box 19)
  - 1953 April-October, 8 folders (Box 20)
  - 1953 October-December, 4 folders (Box 21)
  - 1954 January-March, 4 folders (Box 21)
  - 1954 April-September, 10 folders (Box 22)
  - 1954 October-December, 5 folders (Box 23)
  - 1955 January-April, 4 folders (Box 23)
  - 1955 April-November, 5 folders (Box 24)
  - 1956-1957 (Box 24)
  - 1958 (Box 24)
  - 1959, 2 folders (Box 24)
  - 1960, 2 folders (Box 25)
  - 1961, 3 folders (Box 25)
  - 1962 (Box 25)
  - 1963, 3 folders (Box 25)
  - 1964, 4 folders (Box 26)
  - 1965, 6 folders (Box 26)
  - Undated (Box 26)
  - Lists of correspondents
    - 1936-1938 (Box 26)
    - 1940-1941, 1946, 1949 (Box 26)
    - [1941?] for mayoral campaign?] (Box 26)
    - 1951-1959 (Box 26)
    - 1960-1961, 1964 (Box 26)
    - Undated, 2 folders (Box 26)
- Correspondence of others
  - June 12, 1931-November 10, 1965 (Box 26)
  - December 14-16, 1965 (Box 26)
  - December 16-30, 1965 (Box 28)
  - December 1965-January 5, 1966 (Box 28)
  - January 6, 1966-January 31, 1967 (Box 28)
- Financial records
  - 1941-1943 (Box 28)
  - 1946-1949 (Box 28)
  - 1950-1953 (Box 28)
  - 1954 (Box 28)
  - 1960-1965
- Writings
  - Articles
    - "Benito Mussolini," Outlook, CXXXII, no. 23 ( November 29, 1922), 574-575 (Box 29)
    - Publicity re: Benito Mussolini, World, undated; printed material (Box 29)
    - "The Corsi Affair", undated (Box 29)
    - "Fascism Turned Anarchy to Order," World, November 4, 1928, 1-2 (Box 29)
    - "From Mine Worker to Ambassador at Washington," Outlook, May 2, 1923, 801-803 (Box 29)
    - "The Immigration Snarl," New Leader, June 18, 1949, 7 (Box 29)
    - "Italian Immigrants and Their Children", March 30-May 27, 1942; [May-June? 1942]; includes background material, correspondence, typescript revised and typescript carbon (Box 29)
    - "Italian-Americans: Vast Majority of Them Are Wholeheartedly Loyal," American Mercury, August 18, 1942, includes typescript carbon (Box 29)
    - "Italy and American 'Millionaires'," Harlemite, September 16, 1922, 1 (Box 29)
    - "Let's Talk About Immigration," Reporter, XII, no. 11 ( June 2, 1955), 22-26 (Box 29)
    - "...Message to HIAS," HIAS Yearbook, 1948, 42 (Box 29)
    - "My Neighborhood," Outlook, CXII, no. 3 ( September 16, 1925), 90-92 (Box 29)
    - "My Ninety Days in Washington," Reporter, XII, no. 9 ( May 5, 1955), 10-17 (Box 29)
    - "New York Stays Out Front," American Federationist, March 1947, 10-17 (Box 29)
    - "Our Bungled Refugee Program," See, XIV, no. 5 ( September 1955), 18-21 (Box 29)
    - "Salute to a Lady," Reader's Digest, March 1957, offprint (Box 29)
    - "Trends in American Immigration," Social Work Today, VII, no. 3 ( December 1939), 7-9., includes typescript revised (October 1939) (Box 29)
    - "United States Immigration Aid Agencies," International Associations, no. 4 ( April 1950), 251-257 (Box 29)
    - "War Loans to Allies Considered America's Contribution to War," Harlemite, I, no. 51 ( September 23, 1922), 1 (Box 29)
    - "Weak Link In Our Immigration Laws," Philadelphia Inquirer Parade, August 1, 1948, 2 (Box 29)
    - "Your State: A Good Neighbor", [January 1954]; typescript revised (Box 29)
  - Articles on Mexico
    - Publicity, Outlook, CXXXVI, no. 1; inside back cover, CXXXVI, no. 3, 106, January 2, 1924; January 16, 1924 (Box 30)
    - "Mexico: a Democracy in the Making," Outlook, CXXXVI, no. 2 ( January 9, 1924), 58-60 (Box 30)
    - "Agrarian Reform in Mexico," Outlook, CXXXVI, no. 4 ( January 23, 1924), 142-143 (Box 30)
    - "Where Labor Follows the Red Flag," Outlook, CXXXVI, no. 6 ( February 6, 1924), 229-231 (Box 30)
  - Articles on Yugoslavia
    - Background material, October-November 1949; printed material (Box 30)
    - (1) "Meet Marshal Tito", undated; typescript revised and typescript carbon (Box 30)
    - (2) "Jugoslavia: A People's Democracy", undated; typescript revised and typescript carbon revised (Box 30)
    - (3) "Workers and Peasants in Jugoslavia", undated; typescript revised and typescript carbon revised (Box 30)
    - (4) "The Five-Year Plan", undated; typescript revised and typescript carbon (Box 30)
    - (5) "The Cold War with Russia", undated; typescript revised and typescript carbon revised (Box 30)
    - (6) "Jugoslavia's Foreign Policy", undated; typescript revised and typescript carbon (Box 30)
  - Books
    - Eduardo Corsi Parla, New York, 1942, reproduction (Box 30)
    - In the Shadow of Liberty
      - Correspondence, March 19, 1934-May 22, 1935; February 28, 1955 (Box 30)
      - Book reviews, January 20-April 25, 1935; printed material (Box 30)
      - Quotations, July 1963; June 1969; printed material (Box 30)
    - Paths to the New World: American Immigration: Yesterday, Today and Tomorrow, New York, 1953 (Box 30)
  - Interviews
    - John Foster Dulles, Oral History Project, Princeton University Library, April 2, 1965; reproduction of typescript (Box 30)
      Princeton University Library supplied Syracuse University Library Manuscript Division a copy of the interview with Mrs. Corsi's knowledge and consent, and accepted the following restrictions on the use of the transcript: "That it may be read in the Princeton [Syracuse] University Library, quoted from, and cited only by serious research scholars accredited by Princeton [Syracuse] University. The Princeton [Syracuse] University Library is authorized to supply a single photocopy to any scholar thus accredited. This transcript may not be otherwise reproduced, either in whole or in part, by microphoto, typewriter, photostat, or any other device, except by the heirs, legal representatives, or assigns of Commissioner Edward Corsi."
  - Lectures
    - "Selections from Italian-American Literature", December 1937; undated; typescript revised, notes, typescript (Box 30)
  - Letters to the editor
    - "Why Work?", undated; printed material (Box 30)
  - Notes
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 30)
  - Radio broadcasts (in Italian)
    - "Io Sono Americano!", 1941, March 9; printed material revised (Box 30)
    - Untitled, 1941, May 16; typescript carbon (Box 30)
    - Untitled, re: Italians and aliens, 1941, May 25; typescript and typescript revised (Box 30)
    - Untitled, 1941, June 1; typescript revised (Box 30)
    - Untitled, 1941, June 5; typescript carbon (Box 30)
    - Untitled, 1941, July 6; typescript revised (Box 30)
    - Untitled, 1941, August 31; typescript revised (Box 30)
    - "In Onore di Cristoforo Colombo", 1941, October 12; typescript (Box 30)
    - Untitled, 1941, November 8; typescript revised (Box 30)
    - Untitled, 1941, December 28; typescript revised (Box 30)
    - "...inaugurazione della stagione 1941-1942 al Metropoliton O.H.", [1941?]; typescript revised and typescript carbon (Box 30)
    - Untitled, [ca. 1941?]; typescript revised (Box 30)
    - Untitled, [ca. 1941?]; typescript revised (Box 30)
    - Untitled, [ca. 1941?]; typescript carbon (Box 30)
    - Untitled, re: Social Security, [ca. 1941?]; typescript revised (Box 30)
    - Untitled, 1942, January 31; typescript and typescript carbon revised (Box 30)
    - Untitled, 1942, April 3; typescript carbon revised (Box 30)
    - Untitled, 1942, April 25; typescript carbon revised (Box 30)
    - "In Occasione del XX Anniversario della Stazione WOV", 1947, April 19; typescript revised (Box 30)
    - "The Castelli Family", Undated; typescript carbon (Box 30)
    - "La Colonia Agricola di Vineland", Undated; typescript carbon (Box 30)
    - "I am an American Boy", Undated; typescript revised (Box 30)
    - "Il Venticinquesimo Anniversario di una Grande Fondazione Americana", Undated; typescript revised (Box 30)
    - Untitled, Undated; typescript and typescript carbon (Box 30)
  - Reports